<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Kings most excellent Majestie. The humble remonstrance and renewed petition of the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly of the Kirk of Scotland, from their meeting at Edinburgh, the second day of June. 1643.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4271dA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E249_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212545</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871152</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871152</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159059</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159059)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 43:E249[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Kings most excellent Majestie. The humble remonstrance and renewed petition of the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly of the Kirk of Scotland, from their meeting at Edinburgh, the second day of June. 1643.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Bryson.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 20th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159059:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO THE KINGS Moſt Excellent Majeſtie. THE HVMBLE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONSTRANCE AND RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEWED PETITION OF the Commiſsioners of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſembly of the <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> from their meeting at <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> the ſecond day of <hi>June.</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p>EDINBURGH, Printed by ROBERT BRYSON. 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:159059:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159059:2"/>
            <head>To the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie. The humble <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> and renewed <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Commſsioners</hi> of the Generall Aſſembly of the Kirke of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from their meeting at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> day of <hi>June. 1643.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the manifold and preſſing neceſſitie of the dutie of our place and truſt, did conſtrain us, in theſe diſtempered and dangerous times, in moſt humble manner, To direct our earneſt ſuplication to your Majeſtie, for ſuch remedies as we conceive to be moſt fit for us to propone, And being applyed by your Majeſties own hand, might both for cure and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention prove moſt effectuall: So are we enforced by the ſame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie growing daily to the greateſt extremity, In all humilitie and earneſtneſſe, To renew not only our prayers to God, but our Petitions to your Majeſtie. <hi>For Sions ſake can we not hold our peace, and for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems ſake we will not reſt, untill the righteouſneſſe thereof go forth as brightneſſe, and the ſalvation thereof as a lamp that burneth.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in your Majeſties anſwer to our former Petition we meet with a multitude of prejudices and exceptions againſt us and our humble deſires, we will crave leave, firſt to remove theſe out of the way: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the full expreſſion of them by your Majeſtie to be no ſmall favour, and being confident, after we have expreſſed our ſelves in the truth and integritie of our hearts, both to give unto and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159059:3"/>from your Majeſtes Juſtice and goodneſſe the greater ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>And firſt, although there be good reaſon for printing of Anſwers and Replies, the Petition being before printed, yet we acknowledge that your Majeſtie hath juſt cauſe to finde fault with that publiſhing of our Petition in print (which is mentioned in the introduction to your Majeſties anſwer) And if it had been done by our command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, counſell or knowledge, we had not onely given yaur Majeſtie juſt provocation, and fallen in an errour contrary to the nature of a Petition, and to the right diſpoſition of Petitioners, but alſo had uſed means contrary to our own ends, in publiſhing a programe of our dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of obtaining our deſires, or in giving a publike teſtimonie that we were aiming at ſome other thing then what we profeſſed to ſeek, And therefore we are ſo far from excuſing that form of doing, that we judge our ſelves to be wronged thereby.</p>
            <p>Another fault much more intollerable is objected againſt us: <hi>The bitterneſſe and ſharpneſſe of ſome expreſsions which may be interpreted by your Majeſties wel affected Subjects not to be ſo agreeable to that regard and reverence which is due to your Majeſties perſon, and the matter it ſelf to be reprochfull to the honour and conſtitution of that your Majeſties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Whether the matter of the Petition be reproachfull ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the particulars appear: But for the expreſions we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the whole Petition and can finde no word of that kinde. We rather did fear the cenſure of fauning and flattering words, which your Majeſtie may remember were ſometime put upon our ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. Our deſire was to keep within the bounds of that liberty which beſeemeth the Miniſters of Chriſt, and if any word have eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us which we cannot ſee, it was contrary to our intention: for we know that we ſhould neither ſpeak evill of dignitie nor unreverently unto them. The like report hath been made to your Majeſtie of our preaching and prayers, but when the delators are tryed, they will be found either malicious againſt us for reproving their faults; Or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no other way of inſinuation, too officious to your Majeſtie, or to others whom they deſire to pleaſe, or ſo blinded with ſelf-love, that they think Preachers ſhould ſpeak like Paraſites; or ſo undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, that when we profeſſe our deſire to the Reformation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> we are fanſied by them to preach or pray againſt the King and his Royall authority. We fear God, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159059:3"/>honour the King, And have learned not onely to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and the King, but alſo (againſt the old ſophiſtication now revived) betwixt the pictures of the Emperour, and the images of the falſe gods, craftily inſert into them, and know the way how to honour the King without ſuch a mixture and confuſion. Slowneſſe to beleeve an evill report, and the conſtructing of things doubtfull is one of your Majeſties Royall praiſes, of which the faithfull Miniſters of this Kirk deſire, againſt ſlanders and ſuſpitions to have the experience: which will prove profitable for your Majeſties honour and obedience, and our peace and quietneſſe. <hi>As the North-wind driveth away rain: So doth an angry countenance a back-biting tongue. Righteous lips are the delight of Kings: and they love him that ſpeaketh right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the interpoſing of the Generall Aſſembly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and our intermedling by commiſſion from them in the Kirk of <hi>England;</hi> We humbly intreat your Majeſty, to conſider of the reaſons of this our doing. 1. Although the Kirks of one Nation be diſtant in place from the Kirks of another Nation, yet are they uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the heart and ſpirit, and are generally but one body and Kirke, and muſt as Siſters of one Mother keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace: whence ariſeth the communion of all Gods graces and bleſſings amongſt the Kirks, that they may not only help, comfort and refreſh: but adviſe, admoniſh, exhort, warne and reprove one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, ſo farre as need requireth, and their Chriſtian love and ability reacheth. Yet avoiding both ambition and confuſion: there being a co-ordination between Kirks of diverſe Nations, but no ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: We have not preſumed to paſſe the limits of this Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: having proceeded by way of charity, and in a <hi>miniſteriall,</hi> or rather brotherly manner, not by authority or <hi>magiſterially:</hi> by way of humble ſupplication to your Majeſty, Declaration to the Houſe of Parliament, and advice and exhortation to ſuch of our brethren of the Miniſtery as were beſt known unto us: very far from uſurpation or juriſdiction. 2. Our humble Petition to your Majeſty, and our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration to the Parliament, were nothing elſe, but a proſecution of the demand made by the Commiſſioners of this Kingdom, and a preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Anſwer given by your Majeſty and the Parliament, in the laſt Treaty; which filled us with hope of what was then demanded, ſince followed by diverſe Declarations, and now again deſired. 3. The experience of the ſufferings of this Kirk from the doctrine, forme of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159059:4"/>worſhip and government of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> doth beget feares of the like hereafter, which maketh our petition to be unto us a neceſſary meane of ſelfe-preſervation. 4. Our encouragements from your Majeſties Letter to the generall Aſſembly, and the Declaration of the Houſe of Parliament, deſiring them to concurre in petitioning your Majeſty for ſetling one confeſſion of Faith, one directory of the publike worſhip, and one Catechiſme in all the three Kingdomes, <hi>as a meane to advance the honour and ſervice of God, enlarge the greatneſſe, power, and glory of the King, confirme the peace, ſecurity, and proſperitie of all his good Subjects, make way to the reliefe and deliverance of the poor afflicted Kirks abroad, and to the totall aboliſhing of the uſurpation and tyrannie of Rome.</hi> 5. The paterne we have of this Chriſtian duty both by word and writing in the Kirk at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Kirk at <hi>Antioch,</hi> which was firſt Crowned with the name of Chriſtians, The one of which were <hi>Jewes,</hi> and the other <hi>Gentiles;</hi> And in diverſe other Kirks recorded in Scripture, many Precedents alſo in antiquity before the Kirks did contend for primacie, or knew any preheminence one over another. Many examples of other reformed Kirks; And the practiſe of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> diverſe times after the Reformation writing into <hi>England</hi> againſt the ceremonies, and for union againſt the Papiſts and their confederats banded together by the bloudy league of <hi>Trent.</hi> Theſe and the like reaſons we conceive did ſufficiently authorize us in all that we have done, not as Directors or Judges, but as ſupplicants and humble adviſers. <hi>In that day ſhall there be an high way out of</hi> Egypt <hi>into</hi> Aſſyria (from one Kirk and Nation of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to another) <hi>And the</hi> Egyptians <hi>ſhall ſerve with the</hi> Aſſyrians, <hi>whom the Lord of Hoſtes ſhall bleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this and the like grounds, have letters been ſent profeſſedly, between ſome godly, loyall and peaceable Miniſters of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> and the Generall Aſſembly here, and their Commiſſioners: One of the meanes intended for the good of Religion in both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms againſt Sects and Shiſmes, admitted and approven by your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Commiſſioners in the Generall Aſſembly, and which for the forme of doing is innocent, and may be profitable, unleſſe the matter be nocent and hurtfull, and thereby deſerves cenſure. Wee wiſh wee were able by our Letters, Declarations, or Petitions; To reduce all the Reformed Kirks to a perfect conformity, to ſuppreſſe all the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, Superſtition and Tyranny of Papiſts, and the Paganiſme of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159059:4"/>Turkes and infidels, and would not doubt of your Majeſties Royall approbation notwithſtanding all the Lawes ſtanding to the contrary, and plea's could be made for their antiquity, happineſſe and ſtability; Common arguments and colours pretended for every Religion, and of late anſwered to the full in the point of Epiſcopall government, from the verity of Scripture which is true antiquity, and the onely ſolide ground of the happineſſe and ſtabilitie of Religion and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kirk.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners were far from laying upon your Majeſtie any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the Iriſh Rebellion beſeeching God to mainifeſt your Sacred Majeſties innocencie to all the world. They made mention of the miſeries of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for no other end, but to repreſent the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of your Majeſties Kingdoms through the prevailing power of the Popiſh faction; The Britiſh Papiſts at this time being animated by the ſame ſpirit, working upon the ſame principles, enraged with the ſame furies, breathing out the ſame threatnings and ſlaughter, aiming at the ſame ends, and emboldened with the ſame preſumption, with the Papiſts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> their confederates. And withall to preſent our earneſt deſires for a pacification, that both the armies may be ſent againſt that horride rebellion, and peace reſtored to all your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions.</p>
            <p>The expreſsion in our Petition of Unitie in Religion, we have bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the Article in the Treatie accorded unto by your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, from the Declarations of the Parliament; and from the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſembly: By which is meaned no other thing but one Confeſſion of Faith one common directorie for worſhip, and one Catechiſme. The Papiſts may know that the true Kirk in all ages, hath been trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with differences and contentions, as great as any now, againſt the Reformed Kirks, which many of the godly have lamented &amp; ſtudied to compoſe, and (as it was written of ſome heretikes of old) <hi>They them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſacrifice in ſchiſme and diſſention, and greet the world with the name of peace, whom they drive from the peace of ther ſalvation.</hi> They therefore cannot hence authrize their ſcandal againſt the remformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: yet the ſmalleſt differences of practiſe and diverſitie of the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, are matter of ſtrife to the contentious, of hinderance of edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ignorant, of ſtumbling to the weak, and of grief to the godly, when thereby they ſee againſt religious Unitie and Chriſtian love, the bowels of the Kirk rent aſunder, and people ſcandalouſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159059:5"/>in ſome parts of the worſhip of God: All which evill, might be perfectly cured in all your Majeſties dominions, the mouthes of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſtopped, Schiſme and Separation hereafter prevented, and the face of the Kirk filled with true beauty and ſplendor, to your Majeſties greater glory, and the greater terrour of all your enemies: by this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and never enough deſired Unity in Religion: Without which ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſciences being freed from conſtraint may be in ſome degree eaſed by your Majeſtie, but ſhall never have reſt, and be ſatisfied, nor ſhall the rent of the Kirk ariſing from different or contrary practiſes be cured, but ſhall from time to time increaſe.</p>
            <p>Concerning uniformity in Kirk government, our hopes thereof and of the unity of Religion grounded upon the the Article of the Treatie, made this Kirk and Kingdom to enter into the more ſtrict amity and friendſhip with <hi>England.</hi> And that the amitie and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip builded upon ſuch a foundation might be the more firme and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, they have ſince preſſed the ſame by their Petitions and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, in all humilitie and love, without any bitterneſſe of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Onely they have declared the government of the Kirk by Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies in their ſtrong and beautifull order, and ſubordination to be by Divine right, and that as Prelacie is confeſſed in this your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Anſwer to be the rule of humane policie, ſo to be almoſt univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally acknowledged by the Prelates themſelves, and their adherents to be but a humane inſtitution, intoduced by humane reaſon, and ſetled by humane Law and Cuſtome, for ſuppoſed convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; which therefore by humane authoritie, without wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any mans conſcience, may be altered and aboliſhed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo great a neceſſity, as is, a hearty conjunction of all the reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Kirks, a firm and well grounded peace, between the two Kingdoms, formerly divided in themſelves and betwixt themſelves by this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wall, and a perfect Union of the two Kirks in the two Nations; which although by the providence of God in one Iſland, and under one Monarch, yet ever ſince the Reformation, have been at greater diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the point of Kirk government (which in all places hath a powerfull influence upon all the parts of Religon) then any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Kirks, although in Nations at greateſt diſtance, and under d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Princes. Papacie is the greateſt cauſe of ſchiſme in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Kirk, and Epiſcopacie deviſed by man, to be a cure, the greateſt cauſe of ſchiſme in the Reformed Kirks.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:159059:5"/>
            <p>As the mutuall relation and conjunction of true Eccleſiaſticall and Civill government is a corroboration of both, ſo do we conceive that both are much weakened in their proper functions by that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixture of the Eccleſiaſticall government with the Civill State. And as we know the principles of Prelacy to be Popiſh, and contrary to the principles of Reformation: So have we reaſon to beleeve, that ſuch an intermixture is not for your Majeſties honour, while they maintain and profeſſe that Monarchie cannot ſubſiſt without Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: And that Prelacie had not been caſt out of the Parliament, if it had been profitable there; And thought fit to be altogether abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, if it had not been an unprofitable burthen to the kingdom, and pernicious to the civill State and Common wealth: As is contained more fully in the Declaration of both Houſes of Parliament to the Generall Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>The following of humane inventions, without and againſt Scripture, and the ambition and covetouſneſſe of Kirkmen, were obſerved of old, to be the corruptions which made many to call upon the Pope, and the chief guides of the Kirk, at that time for a Reformation: but all in vain, for that had been their own ruine, to which in humane reaſon, they would never willingly have conſented. That upon the ſame cauſes and corruptions there is a neceſſity of reformation of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> Is as unanimouſly confeſſed, as it is univerſally acknowledged, that it is unlikely if not impoſſible; to be obtained in the regular and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way: Upon the reaſon expreſt afterward in your Majeſties anſwer. <hi>Becauſe in the common and ordinary way the paſsion or intereſt of particular men will impoſe upon the publict:</hi> For what greater private intereſt then benefits and dignities? Who more intereſſed in theſe then Biſhops, Deans, Arch-deacons and ſuch ordinary members of the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And who can be more ſueyed, and byaſſed with paſſion, then ſuch as have this intereſt? Whether this be appliable to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſe places and dignities are uncontroverted, and unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, it is not for us to judge: but this we know, when the corruptions of the Kirk are grown to ſuch an height, that ſhe can neither bear her diſeaſes, nor endure the remedies, it is the dutie of the Magiſtrate and civill authoritie, by the advice of the more ſound, and ſincere part of the Kirk and Miniſterie, to endevour a Reformation, ſince no Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, worthie of that name, can be expected from the corrupt Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, nor hath at any time Religion been that way in any tolerable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159059:6"/>meaſure reformed: When the evils are extraordinary, the remedies muſt be other then ordinary. Scripture, reaſon, and experience of the Kirk teach in ſuch an exigence of Reformation and extremitie of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and contentions, to call a Synod of the beſt Divines, beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the will of God in Scripture, freeſt of humane inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and innovations, and farreſt from pride and avarice; which are the evils to be purged out, and for afterward prevented; And who againſt al Sects and Shiſmes, unfainedly ſeek the peace and unity of the Kirk, which by all good meanes both for it ſelf, and for the truths ſake, is to bee procured and preſerved. When by this remedie faithfully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, and accompanied with prayers, and tears of repentance; the worſhip of God and the government of the Kirk are ſetled, not after the rules of humane policie, but according to Scripture, there is hope that God wil end his controverſie with <hi>England,</hi> and bliſſe the treaties of peace betwixt your Majeſtie and your Parliament; which is now our humble deſire, and when it cometh to paſſe, ſhall be the univerſall rejoycing of all your good people.</p>
            <p>We ſhould be not onely unchriſtian but diſloyall and unnaturall, if we were not affected, and afflicted, with your Majeſties many ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and the troubles of your Kingdoms, and did not heartily wiſh that your Majeſtie were peſent in your Parliament, aſſembled in the moſt peaceable and Parliamentarie way, to your Majeſties greater glorie, and their greater ſtrengthening, for the good of the Kingdom. For the preſent, the houſes of Parliament have profeſſed in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration to the Generall Aſſembly, their deſires and willingneſſe, to ſettle ſuch a Reformation of the Kirk; as ſhall be moſt agreeable to the word of God, and moſt apt to procure and conſerve an happy union with the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> in a peaceable and parliamentarie way; And have paſſe their bills in both houſes without contradiction againſt Epiſcopall governement, and offered them to your Majeſtie for obtaining your Royall conſent: This is the peaceable and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentarie way, meant by us, and mentioned in our petition, which we truſt can give your Majeſtie no juſt offence.</p>
            <p>Although the Miniſters of the Goſpel have authority in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to preach and write not only exhortations, and bleſſings, but alſo threats, and ſentences of judgement, againſt Kings and Kingdoms, which howſoever they be bitter and unpleaſant for the peſent (and therefore ſeldom miniſtred to princes) may prove very profitable,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159059:6"/>and cordiall afterward: Many had periſhed in their ſins if it had not been told them that they were to periſh; faithfull are the wounds of a friend, but the kiſſes of an enemie are deceitfull: and he that rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, afterwards ſhall find more favour then hee that flattereth with the tongue. Yet upon good reaſon have we abſtained from this ſtrain of denuncing of judgement againſt your Majeſty, having onely from the conſcience of our duty in anguiſh of our ſouls, faithfully repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the duty and danger with our earneſt deprecation of the wrath not only now incumbent, but yet ſeven times more imminent to your Kingdomes, which we daily more and more apprehend, ſhall enſue, unleſſe by a through Reformation of Religion and manners it bee timeouſly prevented. By this our liberty we have delivered our owne ſoules, and endevoured to deliver your Majeſty and your Dominions from the preſent and future judgements, which both love and feare conſtrain us now again; To entreat your Majeſty to hearken unto.</p>
            <p>As we cannot deny, but do reverently acknowledge the influence of many and great bleſſings from heaven upon the reigne of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> and your Majeſties Father of bleſſed memory: So doe we not doubt, but your Majeſty in your Chriſtian and Royall wiſedome will conſider: that the ſupreme providence which hath ſet your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie after them upon the Throne, hath appointed a time for every action. <hi>A wiſe mans heart diſcerneth both time and judgement,</hi> and where it is not diſcerned, <hi>the miſery of man,</hi> wreſtling with invincible providence, <hi>is great upon him.</hi> The many bleſſings upon the Kings of <hi>Egypt, Babylon,</hi> and other Princes, were interrupted in the time of their ſucceſſours, which oppoſed the deliverance of the people of God from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage, the <hi>Babylonian</hi> captivity, the fooliſhneſſe of <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> and the tyrannie of Popery, when the time of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance was come. Many of the godly before your Majeſties reigne have deſired and ſupplicated the Parliament for a Reformation, but the deſires were never ſo univerſall as now; Prelacie never ſo inſolent, nor the evils thereof ſo well knowne and ſo deeply felt; nor was it ever voted out of the Parliament, nor agreed in Parliament to be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the Kirk; nor ſtood meerly upon the Royall conſent of the King, till this time. <hi>Arminianiſme</hi> hath entered, Papiſtry hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, Sectaries have multiplied, ſufferings have abounded, Tender conſciences diſquieted with old and new ceremonies, much more of late then before, that all eyes may ſee how many things concur now to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159059:7"/>make a neceſſity of reformation. It is the never dying honour of your Majeſties late Progenitors above others that were before them, that they did begin, continue and preſerve reformation, and ſhall be your Majeſties greateſt and immortall glory to perfect it, with <hi>Joſiah</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing to imped or obſcure the glory of God: An happineſſe which the people of God in this Iland have long waited for, which God calleth for at your hands, and we truſt hath reſerved for our times, as a ſpeciall and incomparable honour to your Majeſtie above the beſt Princes, and matter of joy to your people above all other in former ages.</p>
            <p>As the continuall comfort and daily ſenſe of the ineſtimable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, of the Reformation of this Kirk in worſhip and government, ſhould ſtir up our hearts, to the love of God, whoſe hand principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, did bring it about, in a way full of marvels, and full of mercies, And thankfulneſſe to your Majeſtie, whom we look upon, not as a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked aſſenter unto alterations, but as a prime inſtrument of ſetling a bleſſed Reformation in this Kirk; So doth the ſame comfort and ſenſe excite in us, a fear to loſe that which we ſo much love, in a way where in it hath run hazard before. Our fears are not counterfeit, to bring any deſigne of our own, nor politick, or created in us, by the authoritie of any aſſertion of others, to bring any deſigne of theirs to paſſe, nor panick, or maginarie, to torment our ſelves without cauſe; But are true and reall, grounded upon reaſon, which teacheth to beware of contagion, in ſo neer a vicinitie, and where there is ſo frequent commerce and converſing upon by-paſt experience of evils from Engliſh Prelacie, ever ſince the beginning of Reformation, and upon preſent and daily taſting of the fruits, which partly of its own corupt nature, and partly through the coruptions of men, It hath brought forth &amp; fomented. And though the Petitioners cannot judge, nor ſhould intermeddle with queſtions about your Maieſties, and the Parliaments power, yet may they well profeſſe from that which every one may underſtand, that the denying of the people their earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, may quench that fervour of affection which is due from a people to their Prince.</p>
            <p>Whether the generality of the Nation deſireth a change of Kirk go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, cannot be better known then by the deſires and Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the repreſentative bodie of the Kingdome, nor can it be better defined what government ſhall be eſtabliſhed, than in Synod of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159059:7"/>and godly Divines. Our part is to wiſh the pattern in Scripture and the example of the beſt Reformed Kirks to be followed, and to pray that God by his Spirit may lead them into all truth: being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that reformation having begun by your Majeſties authority at the head and chiefeſt parts, all ſectaries, and all the inferiour mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers may be quickly by a Synod brought to ſuch order as may conſiſt with truth and with the peace of the Kirk.</p>
            <p>It was farre from our intentions by the generall expreſſions of our Petition againſt Papiſts, To charge your Majeſty with complyance and favour to their opinions. We doe from our hearts bleſſe God for all that your Majeſty hath done both here and in England againſt them, and for ſo free and ample a teſtimony of your Majeſties de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the Queenes converſion. Jealouſies of that kinde, and hopes in the hearts of ſuch as are popiſhly affected, of their prevailing power, proceed from the power of Papiſts in Ireland, the preſent poſture of Papiſts armed about your Majeſty in this dangerous time of combuſtion in England, and that for ſo long a time through the connivence or complyance of the Miniſters of eſtate, lawes, have not beene execute againſt them, nor any meanes at all uſed for the Queenes converſion. A neceſſary and eſſentiall duty, from which no oath to the contrary can more give diſpenſation, then any oath of old or late, publike or private, can bind your Majeſty to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Epiſcopacy or any corruption in the worſhip of God, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kirk, when God by his word giveth light and by his providence calleth for a Reformation. All which had neede to be ſeriouſly and tymouſly conſidered. And if the Papiſts be not ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſarmed, the danger is that both in their owne project, and upon the hearing of your Majeſties Declaration to diſarme them, when there ſhall be no more uſe of their ſervice, they band together and bend all their wits againſt a Pacification, till by their gathering and growing to greater ſtrength, they be able to plead in equall termes for themſelves, for their ſhare in the places and honours of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, at leaſt for peace and tolleration, as a reward of all their paines, charges and hazards, pretended to be for your Majeſties ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſafety, but really intended for themſelves and their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. We cannot conceive that loyalty can be without allege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or that Papiſts refuſing to take the oath of allegeance, doe fight in loyalty and allegeance to your Majeſty, but for their owne
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159059:8"/>ends, nor can it be ſafe for Proteſtants to truſt them upon the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of their profeſſion, in any whether inteſtine or forraigne war. In the time of the greateſt forraigne invaſion yeere 88. It was not thought ſafe to arme the Papiſts in defence of the Kingdome. We did not take notice of Papiſts in the other army, in our Petition to your Majeſty, but did in our Declaration to the Parliament, that although they had profeſſed in their Declarations that they had no knowne Papiſts in their Army, yet if any were found to be, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired they might in like manner be disbanded. Browniſts, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, and other ſectaries which are the fruits of Prelacy one way as Papiſts are another, are neither ſo eaſily knowne as Papiſts nor ſo much to be feared: and although they be enemies to Religion and to the peace of the Kirk, we know not whether they have beene ſo conſiderable that the law hath taken ſo farre notice of them as to diſarme them.</p>
            <p>We have ſo ſincerely and from the inward of our ſpirits, with our hearts and hands lifted up to the moſt high God the ſearcher of hearts, ſworne the care of the ſafety of your Majeſties perſon, and of your greatneſſe and authority, which we have alſo witneſſed in our Declarations to the Houſes of Parliament, that our hearts within us were wounded when we did heare of the danger your Majeſties perſon was in the 23 of October. And as we doe with the Houſes of Parliament (as is expreſſed in their Declaration) rejoyce and heartily praiſe God for your ſafety, So doe we not ceaſe to pray for your Majeſties preſervation in the midſt of ſo many dangers, and for a ſpeedy deliverance by a happy peace, which we truſt ſhall bury that blacke and unnaturall day ſo unhappie and dangerous both to your Majeſtie and your people in eternall oblivion, and therefore not to be paralelled by us with the unparalelled plot of the 5. of November never to be forgotten.</p>
            <p>We have detained your Majeſtie longer then your great affaires of governing Kingdomes in the time of warre could well permit, but not ſo long as the charge committed to us by the Generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, and the importance of our Petition, which is of religious and publike concernment doth require. The crime of bitterneſſe and want of reverence to your Majeſty, the challenge of uſurpation, the aſperſion of ſo much and manifold miſtaking, we would beare the more patiently if we were to be conſidered as private and particular
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159059:8"/>perſons, and not as Commiſſioners of publike truſt: And yet doe beare the more patiently, becauſe we take them (and in this no man ſhall perſwade us that we are miſtaken) to proceed from the pen of the writer, and not from your Majeſties juſtice and goodneſſe, unto which we are bold to appeale from his unjuſt cenſure, and from ſuch ſlanderous tongues and pens as by traducing the preaching and prayers of the miniſtery here of diſloyalty or ſedition, doe much wrong us, your Majeſtie much more, and truth and peace moſt of all. Your Majeſty in your wiſedome will conſider what ſuch Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants are ſeeking, and in your juſtice will rather beleeve our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like teſtimony, in things beſt knowne to our ſelves and to our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary hearers, then any private information flowing from the malice of ſome, or the weakneſſe of others. And now in your royall good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will be graciouſly pleaſed to ſuffer us your Majeſties moſt humble and faithfull Subjects to fall downe at your feet, and with all earneſtneſſe to renew our Petition, eſpecially that of Unity in Religion, and uniformity of Kirk Government in all your Majeſties Dominions, which we conceive to be principally, intended by divine Providence in theſe unhappy diſtractions and troubles of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Kingdomes; And to this effect for ſuch an Eccleſiaſticall Aſſemblie, as hath beene formerly deſcribed and deſired: A meane ſo pious, ſo juſt and ſo ordinary in ſuch caſes as malice it ſelfe can have no colour to object againſt your Majeſty for uſing it. And which ſhall ſpeedily bring on a firme and grounded peace, and with peace all other bleſſings ſpirituall and temporall upon your Majeſty and your Kingdomes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker. <hi>Cl. Commiſs. Gen. Aſſ.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
